# Elwin Huaman, M.Sc.







https://elwin.huamanquispe.com/



in http://www.linkedin.com/in/ElwinHuaman/



I am currently working as a research assistant and pursuing a Ph.D. in Computer Science, both are strongly focused on knowledge graphs, their creation, curation, and deployment. I have working experience in researching, teaching, and the maintenance of knowledge graphs in the industry. I have published several articles and co-authored a book. Furthermore, I have participated and been awarded in a conference, hackathon, and datathon. Last but not least, I run several projects, workshops, and presentations related to under-resourced, and endangered languages.

## **Employment History**

- **Lecturer,** Advance Topics in Computer Science, Innsbruck University, **Austria**. 2021 - 2022 In this practical lesson, students learned and applied their programming and research skill to dive into groundbreaking topics and technologies in computer science, e.g. Knowledge graphs.
- **Lecturer**, Online Communication and Marketing, University of Innsbruck, **Austria**. 2020 - 2021 It was focused on learning semantic web technologies, and apply them to online services, e.g., students set up a website, add semantic annotations, and create e-commerce knowledge bases.
- Teacher Assistant, Programming Methodology, University of Innsbruck, Austria. 2019 - 2022 In this pro-seminar, students complement their knowledge of Java programming language. Moreover, students are evaluated weekly, e.g., through presentations, homework, and quizzes.
- 2018 2022 **Researcher**, Semantic Technology Institute (STI), University of Innsbruck, Austria. During this period, I participated in several projects (e.g. MindLab, WordLiftNG), coauthored a book (e.g., Knowledge Graphs), and published several articles (see Google Scholar).
- **Business Development Consultant.** Crnomelj Information Center, **Slovenia**. 2017 - 2018Task: Planning, organizing and implementing activities to promote and develop tourism and business in the Bela Krajina region. In addition, running technology workshops.
- **Lecturer.** Research Center of the National University of Altiplano, Puno, **Peru**. 2016 - 2017 Task: Training teachers in research areas, and use of technologies such as Mendeley (Bibliographic References Manager), SigmaPlot (Data analysis), and DSpace (Repository of data).

## **Education**

- 2019 · · · · Ph.D. in Computer Science (Ongoing). University of Innsbruck, Austria Topic: Knowledge Graph Quality Assessment I research semantic web technologies that can be used for assessing the quality of knowledge graphs, e.g., data modelling, ontologies, knowledge representation, and knowledge curation.
- 2015 2017 M.Sc. in Web Engineering. University of Oviedo, Spain I specialized in developing web technologies using programming languages like PHP, Python, Java, Html, JavaScript. I work on UI design. Also, I did research on semantic web, linked data, RDF, OWL, ontologies, dictionaries, Linked open data.
- M.Sc. in Digital Information Systems. University of Salamanca, Spain 2013 - 2014 I focused on indexing and retrieval systems for digital information, content management and network analysis in digital environments, description, representation, diffusion, consumption, preservation, and organization of digital content.
- 2008 2012 **B.Sc. in Systems Engineering.** National University of Altiplano - Puno, **Peru** My interests were focused on implementing and optimizing complex systems, databases management, and content management systems (CMS). e.g., A platform for managing students and teachers data of the University of Altiplano.

## Languages

English Professional working proficiency
Spanish Native or bilingual proficiency
Quechua Native or bilingual proficiency
Italian Limited working proficiency
German Elementary proficiency

## **Research Publications**

## **Books and Chapters**

Fensel, D., Simsek, U., Angele, K., Huaman, E., Kärle, E., Panasiuk, O., ... Wahler, A. (2020). Knowledge graphs - methodology, tools and selected use cases. Ø doi:10.1007/978-3-030-37439-6

## **Conference Proceedings**

- Huaman, E., & Fensel, D. (2021). Knowledge graph curation: A practical framework. In *Ijckg'21: The 10th international joint conference on knowledge graphs, virtual event, thailand, december 6 8, 2021* (pp. 166–171).

  doi:10.1145/3502223.3502247
- Huaman, E., Tauqeer, A., & Fensel, A. (2021). Towards knowledge graphs validation through weighted knowledge sources. In Knowledge graphs and semantic web third iberoamerican conference and second indo-american conference, KGSWC 2021, kingsville, texas, usa, november 22-24, 2021, proceedings (Vol. 1459, pp. 47-60). Odoi:10.1007/978-3-030-91305-2\\_4

### **Journal Articles**

- Aghaei, S., Angele, K., Huaman, E., Bushati, G., Schiestl, M., & Fensel, A. (2022). Interactive search on the web: The story so far. *Information*, 13(7), 324. Ø doi:10.3390/info13070324
- Huaman, E. (2022). Steps to knowledge graphs quality assessment. CoRR, abs/2208.07779. doi:10.48550/arXiv.2208.07779. arXiv: 2208.07779
- Huaman, E., Huaman, J. L., & Huaman, W. (2022). Getting quechua closer to final users through knowledge graphs. CoRR, abs/2208.12608. 6 doi:10.48550/arXiv.2208.12608. arXiv: 2208.12608
- 4 Angele, K., Fensel, D., Huaman, E., Kärle, E., Panasiuk, O., Şimşek, U., ... Wahler, A. (2020). Semantic web empowered e-tourism. *Handbook of e-Tourism*, 1–46.
- Huaman, E., Kärle, E., & Fensel, D. (2020a). Duplication detection in knowledge graphs: Literature and tools. *CoRR*, *abs/2004.08257*. arXiv: 2004.08257. Retrieved from *O* https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.08257
- Huaman, E., Kärle, E., & Fensel, D. (2020b). Knowledge graph validation. *CoRR*, *abs/2005.01389*. arXiv: 2005.01389. Retrieved from **6** https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.01389

### **Skills**

Coding 📕 Java, PHP, Python, 🖫 KX, ...

Databases 📕 Mysql, Graphdв, SPARQL.

Web Dev 📕 Нтмг, css, JavaScript.

Misc. Academic research, teaching, training, consultation.

# Miscellaneous Experience

### **Selected Projects**

- 2022 · · · · Coordinator, Qichwabase: It is the Quechua language Knowledge Graph project.

  Brings together researchers and Quechua language enthusiasts with the aim of preserving Quechua knowledge, and developing technology for Quechua communities.
- Instructor, Science Clubs in Quechua: We develop in a collaborative and multidisciplinary way the use of the Quechua language for the dissemination of different areas of scientific knowledge. See more: http://clubesdecienciaperu.org/project/cdec54/
- Documentary, Wikipedia Die Schwarmoffensive: It explains the possibilities and limits of Wikipedia through conversations with Wikipedia activists, and those who are critical of it. See: https://www.dw.com/de/wikipedia-die-schwarmoffensive/av-61988535
  - **Researcher**, WordLift NG project: Develops a new platform to deliver Agentive SEO technology to any website. See more: https://wordlift.io/ng/
- Founder, QUIPU [Quechua Language-based Knowledge Graph]: Aims to preserve Quechua knowledge in a structured format. See: https://bit.ly/QUIPUApproach
- Researcher, MindLab project: Develops methods and software tools for modelling and implementing scalability for knowledge graphs. See more: https://mindlab.ai/

#### **Awards and Achievements**

- Best Project Award, 4th Summer Datathon on Linguistic Linked Open Data (SD-LLOD-22): Dictionary LODification using Wikibase: Quechua language, SD-LLOD-22, Cercedilla, Spain. Read more: https://datathon2022.linkeddata.es/
  - **First Prize**, ICTs for Indigenous Languages Hackathon as part of the World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS 2022), *UNESCO*, **France**. https://bit.ly/WSIS-winner
- Best Paper Award, Knowledge Graphs and Semantic Web Conference (KGSWC2021): Towards Knowledge Graphs Validation through Weighted Knowledge Sources, KGSWC2021, Online, Thailand
- Finalists phase, Aporta Challenge 2019: Ideas competition, Ministry of Economy and Business, Spain. See more: https://bit.ly/aporta-2019
  - Grant, 1669 Reise- und Forschungsstipendien for attending Wikimania 2019, Austria
- First Prize, Smart Destinations hackathon (Hack4SD), World Tourism Organization (UNWTO), Spain
- First Prize, University Contest of Talent and Entrepreneurship (CHAMP-U), University of Oviedo, Spain
  - Grant, Peruvian scientists in Europe (SINAPSIS 2017), Germany

#### Certification

- Reading Wikipedia in the Classroom Trainers. Awarded by Wikimedia Foundation
  - **Wikibase and Semantic MediaWiki for data-driven semantics**. Awarded by the European Commission
- 2016 **Mendeley Advisor**. Awarded by ELSEVIER

# **International Activity**

### **Talks**

- Invited speaker: Publishing Structured Quechua Knowledge (Qichwabase), at the Science Clubs in Quechua, Online, Peru
- Presenter: Knowledge Graph Curation: A Practical Framework, at the International Joint Conference on Knowledge Graphs (IJCKG2021), Virtual Event, **Thailand** 
  - Presenter: Towards Knowledge Graphs Validation through Weighted Knowledge Sources, at the Knowledge Graphs and Semantic Web (KGSWC 2021) Conference, USA
  - **Invited speaker**: *Knowledge Graphs: Past, Present, and Future*, at the COPABISI 2021 Conference, National University of Altiplano, **Peru**
  - Invited speaker: Towards an Ecology of Knowledge, at the YACHANA 2021 event, National University of Altiplano, Peru
- Invited speaker: Knowledge Graph basado en el idioma Quechua, at the COPAISI 2020 Conference, National University of Altiplano, **Peru**
- Presenter: QUIPU: Quechua Language based Knowledge Graph, at the Wikimedia 2019 Conference, University of Stockholm, **Sweden**

#### **Reviewer tasks**

- Subreviewer: Semantics and Knowledge track, at the Web Conference (TheWebConf2022), Virtual Event, France
- Subreviewer, at the Knowledge Graphs and Semantic Web (KGSWC2021) Conference, USA
- Subreviewer, at the 12th International Conference on Knowledge Science, Engineering and Management (KSEM2019), Greece
  - Subreviewer, at the 12th International A.P. Ershov Informatics Conference (PSI2019), Russia

#### Collaborative events

- - Organizer: Workshop on Digital Publishing in Quechua Language, at the Science Clubs in Quechua, Online, Peru